Finding Aid for Elizabeth Caroline Crosby Papers 1888-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elizabeth Caroline Crosby Papers 1888-1983, 1935-1980
Crosby, Elizabeth Caroline, 1888-
7 linear feet
The Elizabeth C. Crosby collection consists of the personal and professional papers of a woman pioneer in the field of neuroanatomy. Crosby taught anatomy at the University of Michigan from 1920 to 1958 and authored many respected publications in the field of biology.
85117 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Crosby collection (Donor No. 6864 ) was donated by Dr. Crosby in November 1982; and from the University of Michigan Department of Anatomy (Donor No. 7265 ) in November 1985 and July 1994.
The collection is open for research.
Elizabeth C. Crosby, 1888-1982, professor of anatomy at the University of Michigan, 1920-1958, and the University of Alabama Birmingham was best known for her work in the field of neuroanaotmy. Educated at Adrian College and the University of Chicago, Crosby was the first woman to be named a full professor in the University of Michigan Medical School in 1936. Recipient of the National Medal of Science in 1980.
Elizabeth C. Crosby was born in Petersburg, Michigan in 1888. Crosby received an undergraduate in mathematics from Adrian College and a M.S. in biology from Chicago in 1912. Crosby accepted a position under Dr. G. Carl Huber as in instructor in the department of anatomy at the University of Michigan in 1920. She taught a course in histology in the medical school and assisted Dr. Huber in the medical and graduate school course in neuroanatomy. In addition to teaching, Crosby contributed significantly to the two volume text The Comparative Anatomy of the Nervous System of Vertebrates published in 1936, which is still considered the standard reference work in comparative neuroanatomy for the period prior to 1936. Dr. Crosby continued her progress through the academic ranks of the University of Michigan and in 1936 she was appointed a full professorship in the department of anatomy, becoming the first woman in the medical school to achieve this status. Crosby's excellence in teaching was officially recognized in 1957 when the Galens Society of the University of Michigan Medical School established the Elizabeth C. Crosby annual award for the best preclinical teaching in the school. Her significant accomplishments in research and the quality of her scientific publications were recognized by colleagues all over the world and in 1980 President Carter presented Crosby with the National Medal of Science. Crosby continued as a consultant to the neuroanatomy department after her retirement in 1958, dividing her time between the University of Michigan and the University of Alabama at Birmingham until her death in 1982.
Elizabeth C. Crosby was the only child of Lewis Frederick and Francis Kreps Crosby. A precocious child, Elizabeth had the full attention and love of her middle-aged parents and learned to read early, mastering many adult books before she entered school. She excelled in the elementary and secondary schools of Petersburg, and as a high school graduation present, her father promised her four years of college. She then enrolled in nearby Adrian College and completed her undergraduate degree in three years. Although she had majored in mathematics, Crosby was most fascinated with a single zoology course she had taken, and she thus decided to pursue a graduate degree in biology. Having just one year left on her father's promise, she applied to study under Dr. C. Judson Herrick at the University of Chicago, insisting that she enter the full anatomy program, though she had little preparation in this area as an undergraduate. Displaying the intense drive and dedication which would characterize her entire career, Crosby quickly caught up with her classmates, completing gross anatomy and neuroanatomy with distinction. She received her M.S. degree from Chicago in 1912 and was then granted a fellowship in the anatomy department. The next three years were spent in thesis research and preparation and the University of Chicago awarded her the Ph.D. degree in 1915. Her thesis, "The Forebrain of Alligator Mississippiensis" was a creative, searching and through analysis which became an acknowledged classic.
In 1916, Crosby returned home to Petersburg to be near her ailing mother, and taught Latin, mathematics and zoology at the local high school. She was appointed its Principal in 1916 and Superintendent of Schools in 1918. She introduced an effective course in zoology, and, taking on whatever needed to be done, also served as coach of the basketball team.
After the death of her mother, Crosby resumed her career as a neuroanatomist, accepting a position under Dr. G.Carl Huber as in instructor in the department of anatomy at the University of Michigan in 1920. She taught in the medical school course in histology and assisted Dr. Huber in the medical and graduate school course in neuroanatomy. After the death of her father in 1923, Crosby took a sabbatical to work with the renowned scientist C.U. Ariens Kappers at the Central Institute for Brain Research in Amsterdam. Dr Kappers, the author of a small but well-accepted text in comparative neuroanatomy, subsequently invited Huber and Crosby to join him in its revision. The death of Huber in 1934 placed the burden of this assignment squarely upon the shoulders of Crosby. However, because so much new work of a comparative nature had accumulated internationally no revision could really be adequate and, in her thorough way, Crosby produced The Comparative Anatomy of the Nervous System of Vertebrates, including Man in two volumes, published in 1936. So masterly and comprehensive was its coverage and so correct its interpretations that this work remains today the standard reference work in comparative neuroanatomy for the period prior to 1936. Although Crosby's name is last on the list of authors, it is properly known as her accomplishment.
Dr. Crosby completed her progress through the academic ranks in 1936 when she was appointed full professor in the department of anatomy, becoming the first woman in the medical school to achieve this status. Her career as a professor of neuroanatomy spanned twenty-two years, until 1958, when she retired, becoming professor emeritus. During this tenure she had guided thirty-eight students to the Ph.D. degree (including many female students who were drawn to her as a pioneer in this male-dominated field), and several established scientists had spent residencies of varying duration in Ann Arbor under her tutelage. During this period, her publications continued to be fundamental and comparative and were largely issued jointly with former graduate students, and her teaching became more clinically oriented. She also published two significant and highly acclaimed texts Correlative Neurosurgery (1955) and Correlative Anatomy of the Nervous System (1962).
Upon her retirement, because her contributions to the local neurosurgical department were so significant and appreciated, she was asked to continue as a consultant in neurosurgery. For some years she conducted night classes in neuroanatomy for interns and residents in neurosurgery, neurology, and psychiatry. She attended conferences and ward rounds, aiding in the interpretation of symptoms and in the location of lesions. She conducted research with the permanent staff, particularly Dr. Edgar Kahn and Dr. Richard C. Schneider, and continued her program of publication. Correlative Neurosurgery continued to be brought up to date and its expanded third edition appeared shortly before her death (1982).
In 1963, Crosby began a close professional association with the department of anatomy at the University of Alabama at Birmingham. Crosby's frequent visits to this warmer climate eventually matured into a formal appointment as Professor Emeritus of Anatomy at U.A.B. During her appointment, Crosby was involved in the graduate degree programs of sixteen graduate students in that department as well as with the ongoing research interests of the faculty. These activities were carried on concurrently with her consultantship in neurosurgery at the University of Michigan in a remarkable eighteen year long commutership by air between the two schools. For all the later years, confined to crutches and wheelchairs, she determinedly continued her contributions to beloved students and colleagues.
Dr. Crosby was recognized by all associated with her as a superb teacher. Her lectures were well organized and clear, and although she always arrived to class with copious handwritten notes, she rarely, if ever, consulted them during her presentations. After lecture she always stayed and answered questions until all were satisfied. Few students failed her courses, mainly because she was so diligent in offering help both in and outside of class. Crosby's courses were far from easy, however, as she believed in programs which stretched the mind of even the best students. Her ability to nurture graduate students and encourage them to realize their individual potentials was undoubtedly responsible for the large number of now prominent scientists (including many other female "pioneers" in the field) who have emerged from her tutelage. Crosby's excellence in teaching was officially recognized in 1957 when the Galens Society of the University of Michigan Medical School established the Elizabeth C. Crosby annual award for the best preclinical teaching in the school.
Her significant accomplishments in research and the quality of her scientific publications were also recognized by colleagues all over the world with awards and honors. As early as 1950 she received the Achievement Award of the American Association of University Women and as late as 1972 the Henry Gray Award of the American Association of Anatomists, its most prestigious honor. Invitations to lecture came in numbers to which she could barely respond. She was awarded ten Honorary Doctorates by universities both in the United States and abroad. Her own university honored her with the Solis Award (1926), the Henry Russell Lectureship (1946), the Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award (1956), and the Honorary Doctorate of Sciences (1970). Her honors were culminated with the National Medal of Science presented by President Carter in 1980.
Summary Contents List
Audiovisual Materials - [Box 7]
Awards and Honors - [Boxes 2,5]
Biographical Materials - [Boxes 1,5]
Biographical Materials (collected or researched) - [Box 2]
Conferences - [Box 4]
Correspondence - [Boxes 1-2, 6]
Lectures - [Box 4]
Manuscripts and Articles (Crosby) - [Boxes 3, 5]
Manuscripts and Articles (Others) - [Box 3]
Organizations - [Box 4]
Photographs - [Box 6]
Publishers - [Box 3]
Research (Crosby) - [Boxes 3,5-6]
Research (Others) - [Boxes 3-4]
The Crosby collection consists of two separate acquisitions; Crosby's personal donation of correspondence, biographical and research materials in 1982 and Richard C. Schneider's donation of Crosby's manuscripts, photographs and audiovisual materials in 1994. Dr. Richard C. Schneider, a close friend and colleague of Crosby's, accumulated additional Crosby materials during his unsuccessful attempt to write a complete biography of Crosby; his unfinished manuscript is contained within the collection. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical Materials, Correspondence, Biographical material (collected or researched), Awards and Honors, Manuscripts and Articles, Publishers, Research, Conferences, Lectures, Organizations, Photographs and Audiovisual Materials.
Subjects:
Crosby, Elizabeth Caroline, 1888-; Medicine--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anatomy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School--Faculty.; Neuroanatomy.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Anatomy.; Ariens Kappers, Cornelius Ubbo, 1877-1946.; Crosby, Elizabeth Caroline, 1888-; Herrick, C. Judson (Charles Judson), 1868-1960.; Huber, Gotthelf Carl, 1865-1934.; Medical education.; Neuroanatomy.; Petersburg (Mich.); Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anatomy.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Biographical Materials
  The Biographical Materials series is composed primarily of records relating to Schneider's unfinished biography of Crosby which he had tentatively titled Pioneer Woman Neuroscientist. Included are handwritten and typed manuscripts of this biography, arranged chronologically (in relation to Crosby's life), along with other materials related to Schneider's research of this topic. Schneider's biography of Crosby, though unfinished, represents one of the best sources on Crosby's life, both professional and personal. Schneider attempted, as much as was possible, to uncover information about Crosby's personality and character, as well as her scientific endeavors. This clearly distinguishes Schneider's work from other biographies of Crosby published in scientific journals and the like, which tend to focus exclusively on her professional achievements. Also included are typed transcripts of interviews Schneider conducted with friends and colleagues of Crosby to research his biography (an audio cassette of an interview Schneider conducted with Dr. Isabelle Lockhard is located in the Audiovisual Materials series in box 8), along with correspondence and other miscellaneous records related to this project. In addition to the materials related directly to Schneider's biography of Crosby, other records of a biographical nature have also been included in the Biographical Materials series. Among these are bibliographies and curriculum vitae, Anatomy Dept. Personnel files on Crosby, copies of other biographical articles published on Crosby from various sources, records relating to awards and honors received by Crosby, a file of newspaper clippings documenting various achievements by Crosby, memorial letters written by friends and colleagues, and state records.
  - Biographical file (including cassette of interview with Elizabeth C. Crosby) (Box 1)
  - Pioneer Woman Neuroscientist
    (unfinished biography of Crosby by Richard C. Schneider)
    - Manuscript
      - Childhood to 1900 (Box 5)
      - 1900-1940 (Box 5)
      - 1940-1955 (Box 5)
      - 1955-1960 (Box 5)
      - 1960-1965 (Box 5)
      - 1965-1970 (Box 5)
      - 1970-1980 (Box 5)
      - 1980-1983 (Box 5)
    - Telephone Interviews (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Bentley Research Records (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Curriculum Vitae and Bibliography (Box 5)
  - Anatomy Dept. Personnel Files on Crosby (Box 5)
  - Other Biographies (Box 5)
  - Awards and Honors (Box 5)
  - Clippings (Box 5)
  - Memorial Letters (Box 5)
  - Estate Records (Box 5)
- Correspondence 1935-1979
  The Correspondence series includes acquisitions from both the 1982 and 1994 donations. The 1982 correspondence donation contains letters from 1935-1979 arranged alphabetically by writer. The 1994 donation is comprised primarily of correspondence between Crosby and various colleagues spanning the period from 1970 to the early 1980s, again arranged alphabetically by writer. Most of this correspondence is concerned with research projects Crosby was involved in, and thus complements the documentation provided in the Research series. Also interspersed throughout this series are communications from the 1950s between Crosby and several of her graduate students concerning the preparation of their theses, letters of recommendation, research projects and other academic issues. As such these materials provide some insight into Crosby's great concern and attention to her students' needs and her excellent skills of mentorship. Also of interest are correspondence among the Dean of the Medical School (Furstenburg), the chair of the Anatomy department (Patten) and Crosby in regards to her possible resignation from the University in 1935-1936, her promotion to full professor and her sabbatical in Scotland (1939-1940).
  - A (Box 1)
  - Augustine, James R. (Box 1)
  - B, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Barron, Donald H. (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
  - Congratulations, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - D (Box 1)
  - E (Box 1)
  - F (Box 1)
  - Furstenberg, A.C. (Box 1)
  - G (Box 1)
  - H, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - I (Box 1)
  - J (Box 1)
  - K, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Kappers, J. Ariens (Box 1)
  - L (Box 1)
  - Lockhart, Robert (Box 1)
  - M, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - N (Box 1)
  - O (Box 1)
  - P (Box 1)
  - R (Box 1)
  - S, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - T (Box 1)
  - V (Box 1)
  - W (Box 1)
  - Y (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Furstenburg, Dr. A.C. (Box 6)
  - G (Box 6)
  - Gardner, Dr. W. James (Box 6)
  - Gasser, Raymond F., Ph.D. (Box 6)
  - Hafer, Emma C. (Box 6)
  - Hoerr, Dr. Norman L. (Box 6)
  - K (Box 6)
  - Karp, Muriel (Box 6)
  - Kappers, Dr. J. Ariens (Box 6)
  - Kinney, Dr. Cleveland (Box 6)
  - Krauspe, Dr. Carl (Box 6)
  - P (Box 6)
  - Patten, Dr. Bradley M. (Box 6)
  - Rand, Robert W. (Box 6)
  - Sloane, M.W.M. (Box 6)
  - Slocum, Thedore (Box 6)
  - Woodburne, Russel T. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Biographical material (collected or researched) re:
  The Biographical material (collected or researched) consists of materials acquired in 1982 from Crosby's personal papers. The series includes information Crosby collected on fellow researchers and practitioners in the field of neuroanatomy. The series is arranged alphabetically by name.
  - Bailey, Allan (Box 2)
  - Herrick, Charles Judson (Box 2)
  - Huber, G. Carl (Box 2)
  - Humphrey, T. (Box 2)
  - Kahn, Edgar A. (Box 2)
  - Kappers, Johannes Ariens (Box 2)
  - Spatz, Hugo (Box 2)
- Awards and Honors
  The Awards and Honors series contains several of Crosby's awards acquired in the 1982 accession. Additional awards and honors donated in the 1994 accession can be found in the Biographical Materials series.
  - The Journal of Comparative Neurology. Volume 112 honoring Elizabeth C. Crosby, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Charles Judson Herrick Award 1967 (Box 2)
  - Smith College honorary degree 1967 (Box 2)
  - Medal of Science Award 1979 (Box 2)
- Manuscripts and Articles (Crosby)
  The Manuscripts and Articles series consists of materials received in the 1982 acquisition. The series has been sub-divided into papers generated by Crosby and those of fellow neuroanatomists. The folders in this series labeled "Miscellaneous" are either fragmentary or without identification.
  - Undated
    - Certain Afferent Connections of the Rhinencephalon (Box 3)
    - Comparative Neurology Text (Box 3)
    - A Discussion of Some Interrelated Functions of the Vestibular and the Ocular Motor Systems (Box 3)
    - Evidence for Some of the Trends in the Phylogenetic Development of the Vertebrate Telencephalon (Box 3)
    - The Functional Significance of Certain Duplicate Motor Patterns on the Cerebral Cortex in Primates including Man (Box 3)
    - Nystagmus as a Sign of Central Nervous System Involvement (Box 3)
  - 1955
    - Correlative Neurosurgery Textbook (Box 3)
  - 1962
    - Correlative Anatomy of the Nervous System Textbook (Box 3)
    - The Interplay between Cerebral Hemisphere and Cerebellum in Relation to Tonus and Movement (Box 3)
  - 1964-1969
    - Lists of Publications (Box 3)
  - 1966
    - Tonus and Movements (Box 3)
  - 1969
    - The Anterior Lobe and the Lingula of the Cerebellum in Monkeys and the Man (Box 3)
  - 1972
    - Korsakoff's Syndrome (Box 3)
  - Allison, A.C. (Box 3)
  - Bagchi, B.K. and R.C. Schneider (Box 3)
  - Bucher, Verena (Box 3)
  - Calhoun, Hazel D. (Box 3)
  - Campos-Ortega, J.A. and P.F. de V. Cluver (Box 3)
  - Carey, Josehua H., Elizabeth C. Crosby, and H. Norman Schnitzlein (Box 3)
  - Currier, J. [et al.] (Box 3)
  - DeJong and Elizabeth C. Crosby (Box 3)
  - Furstenberg, A.C. and Elizabeth C. Crosby (Box 3)
  - Gordy, Philip D. (Box 3)
  - Haggqvist, Gosta (Box 3)
  - Haymaker, Webb (Box 3)
  - Humphrey, Tryphena (Box 3)
  - Ingram, W.R. (Box 3)
  - Ingram, W.R. [et al.] (Box 3)
  - Jampel (Box 3)
  - Kahn, E.A. and Elizabeth C. Crosby (Box 3)
  - Lettvin, Jerome (Box 3)
  - Little, Samuel C. (Box 3)
  - McCulloch, Warren S. (Box 3)
  - Magee, K. (Box 3)
  - Moore, Winifred O. (Box 3)
  - Nafe, J.P. and K.S. Wagoner (Box 3)
  - Nissl (Box 3)
  - Perot, Phanor L. (Box 3)
  - Rhodes, J.M. [et al.] (Box 3)
  - Siegel, A. and J.P. Tassoni (Box 3)
  - Slaughter, Graham (Box 3)
  - Tuge, H. (Box 3)
  - Zander, E. and G. Weddell (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Publishers
  The Publishers series consists of materials received in the 1982 acquisition relating to Crosby's working relationships with various publishing companies. The series is arranged alphabetically according to publisher name.
  - Academic Press (Box 3)
  - Grune and Stratton Publishers (Box 3)
  - Macmillan Publishers, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - George Thieme Publishers (Box 3)
- Research (Crosby)
  The Research series documents various aspects of Crosby's career in neuroanatomical investigation and experimentation. Included are records from both the 1982 and 1994 acquisitions, relating to research projects on various topics such as neuroanatomical aspects of space sickness and cell masses of the forebrain (conducted either by Crosby alone or in conjunction with other scientists), research grant applications, typed manuscripts of articles on the anatomy of the human brain, course material developed for an anatomy course which clearly displays the close relationship between Crosby's teaching and her research, hand-drawn neuroanatomical illustrations, handwritten laboratory notebooks (ca. 1920s) and handwritten notes tabulating the results from various neuroanatomical experiments on animals performed by Crosby (ca. 1918). This series is particularly valuable in exemplifying the scope and breadth of Crosby's research efforts throughout her career, and the meticulous care and attention she displayed in all her experimental endeavors. Materials received in the 1982 acquisition are subdivided, research performed by Crosby and research performed by other scientists.
  - Armed Forces Pathology Specimen (Box 3)
  - Bibliographies (Box 3)
  - Case histories, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Cerebral Palsy (Box 3)
  - Finances (Box 3)
  - Hypothalamus (Box 3)
  - Mid-brain experiments (Box 3)
  - Monkey experiment on Tonus (Box 3)
  - Neuroanatomy nomenclature (Box 3)
  - Sleep (Box 3)
  - Spinal Cord (Box 3)
  - Stroke Program (Box 3)
  - Augustine, James R. The Ascending Projections of the Main Sensory Trigeminal Nucleus in the Squirrel Monkey (Box 3)
  - Davie, J. Clayton (Box 3)
  - Kahn, Edgar A. (Box 3)
  - Hooker, Davenport. Early Human Fetal Activity (Box 3)
  - Humphrey, Tryphena (Box 3)
  - The Island (author unidentified) (Box 3)
  - Lewis, Irwin. Candate Function in Primates and Alteration by L-Dopa (Box 3)
  - Langworthy, D.R. (Box 3)
  - Rioch. Diencephalon (Box 3)
  - Vachandada, Forebrain and cerebellum (Box 3)
  - Wilson, S.A. Kinnier. Aphasia (Box 3)
  - Wolfman, E.F., Jr. [et al.]. Experimentally produced Sodium and Chloride Retention occurring with Cerebral Lesions (Box 3)
    (includes photographs)
  - Yakoviev. Stereotonic coordinates (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous research, 3 folders (Box 3)
    (author unidentified)
  - Research Projects
    - "A Theory on Space Sickness: Neuroanatomical and Clinical Correlations" (Crosby and Richard C. Schneider) (Box 5)
    - "Cell Masses of the Forebrain of the Mouse" (Box 5)
    - Gesell and Crosby (Box 5)
    - Midbrain (Bailey, Lauer and Crosby) (Box 5)
    - Parke, Davis and Company (Box 5)
    - Rackham, H.H., Project R281 (DeJong and Crosby) (Box 5)
    - Research Grant Applications (Box 5)
    - Staff (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts
    - "Medulla Oblongata and Pons" (Box 5)
    - "Cerebellum" (Box 5)
    - "Midbrain" (Box 5)